[{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "what act of jq adams boggled clay?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "asking for an immense program of federal improvements", "id": 1},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what did he request aid for?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "manufacturing, agriculture, a national university, a government astronomy observatory", "id": 2},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "why was this risky?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "his lack of jeffersonian origins", "id": 3},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "how was his public style?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "seemingly royalist, convoluted", "id": 4},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "what sections supported tariffs?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "north and west", "id": 5},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "in missouri?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "lead miners", "id": 6},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "in kentucky?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "hemp raisers", "id": 7},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "in new york?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "wool growers", "id": 8},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what is congressional logrolling?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "trading votes in congress, one tariff for another", "id": 9},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "when was tariff of abominations?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1828", "id": 10},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what did the tariff protect?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "wool, hemp, flax, fur, liquor", "id": 11},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "how did the south fail?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "by voting down new englanders' attempts to lower tariffs on raw materials", "id": 12},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "who flipped from no to yes?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "daniel webster", "id": 13},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "who helped new englanders accept the bill?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "martin van buren", "id": 14},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "how did vp calhoun react?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "repudiated the tariff in support of the south", "id": 15},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what did he write", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "the south carolina exposition and protest", "id": 16},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "what theory did he advance?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "nullification", "id": 17},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "with what underpinning?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "lockean contract with states as parties", "id": 18},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what was henry clay's american system", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "each section specialized economically to benefit the whole", "id": 19},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "how would western farmers profit", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "selling crops to eastern cities", "id": 20},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what would benefit everyone", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "building up transportation", "id": 21},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "1820 us population", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "9.6 million", "id": 22},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "why fewer than 250k immigrants 1790-1820", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "european wars, ending of slave trade, doubts about the republic", "id": 23},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "how many immigrants in 1820s", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "150k from europe", "id": 24},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "1830s?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "600k", "id": 25},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "1840's", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1.7 million", "id": 26},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "1850 population", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "23 million", "id": 27},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "percent foreign born", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "10+", "id": 28},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "where did most immigrants come from", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "germany and ireland", "id": 29},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "where else", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "britain and scandinavia", "id": 30},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "pull factors", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "land, wages, freedom", "id": 31},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "push factors", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "starvation", "id": 32},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "where did immigrants land", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "new york, boston, philadelphia", "id": 33},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "where did immigrants work", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "erie canal factory towns, lower delaware valley s.e. of philly, merrimack river n of boston", "id": 34},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "most irish lacked capital for:", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "transportation and starting a farm", "id": 35},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "short run effects of immigration in 30s and 40s", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "depressed living standards and strained social fabric", "id": 36},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what did the first american factory produce", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "cotton thread", "id": 37},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what massachusetts town between 1823-26 grew from 300 to 2000 people", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "lowell", "id": 38},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what rivers did he harness", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "charles, merrimack", "id": 39},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "with what invention", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "power loom", "id": 40},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what industries were mechanizing around 1810", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "iron, wool", "id": 41},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "when did the number of free blacks triple in phillly/quadruple in ny", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1800-30", "id": 42},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "why didn't the us develop working class solidarity", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "frontier, rising economy, ethnic division", "id": 43},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "why did factories employ women and children", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "no skills needed, labor shortage", "id": 44},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "what percent of cotton workers were under 16 in early 1820s", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "half", "id": 45},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "why didnt child labor shock society", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "kept youngsters busy and provided extra income for family", "id": 46},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what replaced women at lowell", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "irish immigrants", "id": 47},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what did the puddling process allow in the 1810s", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "use coal to refine pig iron rather than expensive charcoal", "id": 48},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "how many corporations did states charter from 1781-1801", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "326, few manufacturing", "id": 49}]